Finding Aid for Harry Haywood Papers 1928-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Harry Haywood Papers 1928-1985
Haywood, Harry, 1898-
2 linear feet
851384 Aa/2
African American revolutionary communist and theoretician of Black nationalism, joined Communist Youth League in 1923 and later communist Party U.S.A., studied at Lenin Institute and worked for the Comintern, member of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spanish Civil War, author of Black Liberation (1948) and Black Bolshevik (1977). Papers include correspondence, speeches, text and notes for his writing and Communist Party material.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Gwendolyn Midlo Hall on January 6, 1989. Donor Number 4904
The collection is open for research.
Harry Haywood was born in South Omaha, Nebraska, on February 4, 1898, the son of former slaves. He was a soldier in France during World War I and arrived home during the 1919 riots in Chicago. His experiences led him to become involved in the revolutionary African Blood Brotherhood. Attracted by the Russian Revolution, he joined the Young Communist League in 1923 and later the Communist Party of the United States (CPUSA).
He spent four and one half years in the Soviet Union where he studied at the Lenin School. While working with the Comintern during the late 1920s, he developed a theoretical framework for the Black liberation movement in the United States and South Africa. Haywood's major thesis revolved around his assertion that a Black nation existed in the Deep South of the United States. He considered the Blacks of the Deep South as constituting an oppressed nation, placing the Black struggle in the fight against all forms of national oppression, including the right for self-determination. As the first American communist to assert this position, Haywood helped write the draft for the 1928 resolution on the Negro question in the United States. His draft was adopted by the Communist International with some reluctance by the CPUSA.
In the 1930s he was active in the labor movement and was one of the pioneers in the struggle to organize the Sharecropper's Union and the Scottsboro campaign. In Chicago he organized a massive protest against Mussolini's invasion of Ethiopia. Shortly after the Chicago protest he joined the Abraham Lincoln Brigade fighting against Franco in Spain during the Spanish Civil War. Returning to the United States, he served in the Merchant Marine during World War II and was an active member of the National Maritime Union.
In 1948, his major work Negro Liberation, was published. Following publication he came under attack by the revisionists and fought against dropping the concept of the Black nation in the Deep South and support of the right to self-determination. His beliefs were explained in a pamphlet, For A Revolutionary Position on the Negro Question. He believed that the burgeoning civil rights movement in the South during the 1950s should be understood as a struggle of the oppressed Black nation for self-determination and against imperialism. Thinking that any other understanding would underestimate the revolutionary potential of the movement, thus ending the possibility of an interracial alliance against imperialism, he was expelled from the Communist Party.
Although expelled from the Communist Party, he continued to struggle for socialism. In 1969, in collaboration with his wife, Gwendolyn Midlo Hall, he wrote Toward A Revolutionary Program for Negro Freedom. The author of numerous other articles, his greatest triumph was the publication of his autobiography, Black Bolshevik, in 1977.
Haywood died January 4, 1985, one month before his 87th birthday. His ashes remain in Arlington National Cemetery.
The papers of Harry Haywood consist of two linear feet of materials dating from 1928 to 1985. The collection is arranged topically. It is divided into eight series, including: Autobiography; Articles and Manuscripts; Communist Party Material; Black Conditions and Responses; Speeches and Presentations; Correspondence; Book Contracts and Reviews; and Notes, Fragments and Miscellanea.
Subjects:
Afro-Americans--Michigan.; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Radicalism--United States.; Hall, Haywood, 1898-
- Autobiography
  Autobiography consists of 8 inches of various drafts of his autobiography. These drafts were revised and published as Black Bolshevik.
  - First draft, 10 folders (Box 1)
  - Second draft, 20 folders (Box 1)
- Articles and manuscripts
  Articles and Manuscripts consists of 4 inches of articles and unpublished manuscripts. Included are drafts of his major writings Toward A Revolutionary Program For Negro Freedom, and For A Revolutionary Position on the Negro Question.
  - "For A Revolutionary Position on the Negro Question" Reprint and draft circa 1958 (Box 1)
  - "Towards A Revolutionary Program for Negro Freedom" circa 1964, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Articles 1930-1964, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Rough Draft Manuscript "Criticism of New Left Communism," 1983 (Box 1)
  - Rough Draft Manuscript "The Crisis of the New Communist Movement," 1983 (Box 1)
  - Rough Draft Manuscript "The Three World Theory and the Crisis of the New Communist Movement" 1983 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript "Interview with Edward L. Doty," 1971 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript "Interview with Tony Philips," 1978 (Box 1)
- Communist party material
  Communist Party Material is 2.5 inches of papers, minutes and notes relating to his tenure in the CPUSA. This includes some material relating to the struggle against revisionism.
  - October Plenum of the CC. CP. USA. 1929 (Box 2)
  - Resolutions of the Communist International on the Negro Question in the United States (Box 2)
  - Convention of the Communist Party 1948 (Box 2)
  - The Struggle Against White Chauvinism 1949 (Box 2)
  - "An open letter to the Negro people from the Negro Commission of the Communist Party," 1961 (Box 2)
  - Struggle against revisionism/CPUSA POC circa 1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Afro-American work-Communist Party (Marxist-Leninist) (Box 2)
  - African-American Party of National Liberation Declaration 1964 (Box 2)
  - Resolution of the 3rd National Congress of the October League "The Struggle for Black Liberation and Socialist Revolution" (Box 2)
  - Self-Determination circa 1960 (Box 2)
  - On the concept "Negro": report, response and notes circa 1951 (Box 2)
  - Racism in the United States, an essay by "Democritus," undated (Box 2)
- Black Conditions And Responses (of the 1960s)
  Black Conditions and Responses is 2 inches of outlines, notes and replies to critics of the Black freedom struggle.
  - Outline and chronology of Black Freedom Struggle (Box 2)
  - Black conditions (Box 2)
  - Black Human Rights Manifesto (Box 2)
  - Black leadership and Black elite (Box 2)
  - Black nationalism (Box 2)
  - Black radicalism/ Black radicals (Box 2)
  - Black United Front (Box 2)
  - Memorandum on Democratic Reconstruction of Southern Agriculture (Box 2)
  - Draft Format for the Harlem Unemployment Center (Box 2)
  - Response to Grace and James Boggs (Box 2)
  - Response to R. Palme Dutt and The Colonial Question (Box 2)
  - Reply to Harold Cruse Article (Box 2)
  - Polemics against Harold Cruse (Box 2)
  - Notes and Response to Jay Lovestone (Box 2)
  - Response to George Schuyler (Box 2)
- Speeches and presentations
  Speeches and Presentations consists of 1 inch of copies and drafts of speeches and presentations delivered by Harry Haywood.
  - Various 1950s-1970s, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence consists of 3 inches of letters both sent and received between 1949 and 1985.
  - 1949-1985, 7 folders (Box 2)
- Book publication and reviews
  Book Publications and Reviews is 1 inch of materials relating to contract negotiations, securing a publisher, and various reviews of his books.
  - Book publishing contracts and negotiations 1970s (Box 2)
  - Reviews and Articles about Negro Liberation, 1948-1950 (Box 2)
  - Book publicity and reviews of Black Bolshevik, circa 1977 (Box 2)
  - Michael Goldfield's review of Black Bolshevik, 1980 (Box 2)
- Notes, fragments, miscellanea
  Notes, Fragments and Miscellanea comprises the final 2.5 inches of the collection. It is made up of notes for his writings, handbills and announcements of his death, and other miscellaneous materials accumulated by Harry Haywood.
  - Fragments of writing on Black Power undated (Box 2)
  - Fragments of writing on "Race" undated (Box 2)
  - Notes and fragmentary writings, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Handbills and broadsides circa 1970s (Box 2)
  - Tribute to Harry Haywood 1985 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Photograph of Harry Haywood (Box 2)
  - 1991 addition